Good Morning, Church!
Turn to your neighbour and greet them, "Good Morning!"
Give your neighbour a handshake and say, "Good Morning!"
Give your other neighbour a handshake and say, "Good Morning!"
Give your neighbour behind you a handshake and say, "Good Morning!"
Give your neighbour in front of you a handshake and say, "Good Morning!"
Greet the viewers all over the world on Emmanuel TV, "Good Morning!"
You are all welcome again in Jesus' name.
You may have your seats in the presence of God.
The SCOAN Sunday Service
My name is Chris.
Before I begin today’s message, I want to first and foremost pay tribute to Prophet T.B. Joshua
who is a man I have the incredible privilege to call a mentor.
I came to Nigeria from the UK many, many years ago as a young boy seeking for Jesus
and Prophet T.B. Joshua showed me Jesus.
Not the Jesus of history, of story, of song, the baby Jesus. No!
Prophet T.B. Joshua showed me Jesus in the power of the Holy Ghost.
He taught that the main requirements in making a difference for Jesus is being in love with Jesus.
This is what I see in Prophet T.B. Joshua – a man who loves Jesus
and has sacrificed and surrendered everything for his relationship with Jesus.
And that is why we are here today – because of his love.
He is a great man but his greatness lies not in great material achievements
or great acquisitions or great wealth.
No! His greatness lies in his great love for God.
Here I am today, a product of grace –
in many ways, still that same little boy who came here to serve a big God under a mighty prophet.
Thank You, Jesus Christ!
I want to ask you a question as we go into today's message.
Are you happy to be here today?
I'm not so sure. Let me ask again: Are you happy to be here today?
If you are happy, I would like you to turn to your neighbour and just give them a smile.
Camera, just move around and let's pick them very beautiful smiles.
Just smile at your neighbour. Give them a smile.
Just smile at your neighbour because it is a thing of joy to be here in the presence of God
and I pray that your joy will remain, in Jesus‘ name.
I want to tell you a very short story
in relation to the message God has given me to deliver to you today.
I’m sure people of this generation, our '‚www.com generation' may relate well to this story.
I will just tell you what I saw.
This was several months ago when I was back in the UK.
I was sitting on a train and I saw two young ladies.
Just by their look, by their appearance, you could see that they were depressed.
They were sad; they were moody.
Just name it. It was so obvious.
Everything about them suggested sadness.
These were two ladies you could see who were not materially lacking.
They were using the latest phone, the latest gadget.
They were well looked after but they were sad; they were depressed.
I was overhearing their conversation and I was feeling in my heart,
God look at these two young ladies in their early 20’s, late teenage years.
They had their whole life before them but they were so depressed.
You look at our generation today, you see sadness, depression has spread like wildfire,
especially among young people.
You hear the way in which suicide rates are increasing. It is alarming.
Tell your neighbour, "It is alarming".
As I was watching these two young ladies – I was there going on a journey –
I was looking at these two young ladies and I saw something that shocked me.
It was very surprising.
These were two people that looked extremely sad.
I won't be able to show that expression because...
Can anyone here just give me a sad face?
I'm sorry; I know we have just been happy.
Can someone give me a sad face?
Just for a moment.
Alright. Our gentleman here looks a little bit sad.
Now just imagine...
Don't smile, sir.
Just imagine that you see someone looking sad.
Suddenly, one of them got out their phone and wanted to take a photo, a selfie.
Take a picture of yourself.
These are the people that are depressed, weighed down, clearly anxious, sad.
But suddenly, when they want to take the picture, you should see the smile on their face.
And then, you know the funny thing: Immediately after, they were sad again.
It was mind-boggling, "What is going on?"
And do you know the painful part of this?
They will put this picture on Instagram, Facebook, send it to their boyfriends.
People would think that they were happy; people would think that they were okay.
People would think that they were joyful whereas in reality, they were depressed.
The SCOAN Sunday Service
Please keep praying for this generation because we are living a fake life.
Our joy is for a moment. Our happiness is for a second.
We so often seem to have happiness or joy dependent on our circumstance, dependent on our situation.
That is when we see that happiness.
But I want to ask you a question.
Please, I am not here to make judgement on those two young ladies.
I pray that God will touch their hearts.
I just want to ask everyone here a question.
When you finish your day’s work, you go home and it is time for you to sleep.
You had a long day, you are tired and you lay back down on your bed.
And it is just you and God.
The lights are off. The doors are closed.
The activities of the day have come to a halt.
You are there laying on your bed, reflecting, thinking.
At that moment, do you have joy?
You are looking up at the ceiling.
There is no one there – just you.
At that moment, do you have joy?
Can you laugh without anyone cracking a joke, dance without anyone beating a drum?
Or at that moment, do you feel empty?
The reason why I’m asking this question today:
I am here to warn you about the dangers of sadness.
Whenever you are sad, the devil is at work.
A sad heart is the devil’s workshop.
He can manoeuvre, he can manipulate,
he can sow his seeds of chaos, destruction, division, discord.
He has free reign and rule in your heart as far as you are sad.
When you harbour sadness in your heart, you filter everything through it.
When you are sad, you can abandon jobs, quit relationships –
you don’t give your best; you live below your potential.
You begin to nurse suspicions.
You read meanings into people’s actions and inactions.
If someone greets you today, you say, "Why are they greeting me?"
If someone does not greet you, you say, "Why are they not greeting me?"
Whether they are greeting or not greeting, you read meaning into it.
You are suspicious; everyone becomes a suspect because your heart is sad.
You can’t pray. A sad heart can’t pray.
You may say words but you’re not praying prayer.
People around you may hear you but you’re talking to the air; God doesn’t hear you.
Your heart is sad.
Whenever you are sad, the devil is at work.
When you are sad, you begin to view yourself as a victim.
„Why is this happening to me?
Why am I the one facing this? Why me? Where is God?
Look at this person – God has blessed him, why not me? Me, me, me, I, I, I, why, why, why?“
Focusing on ourselves is the effective instrument used by the devil to blind us from reality.
Do you know what the reality is, children of God?
The reality is, Jesus is the anchor of our souls
and when you remain anchored on Him, attached to Him, connected to Him,
no matter how unsteady your life appears to be, you will remain steady.
Satan knows this.
So, what’s going to happen?
Satan will fight you tooth and nail.
He will use every weapon at his disposal to try and detach you from Jesus,
to try and disconnect you from Jesus because remaining attached to Jesus –
that is where our safety lies, that is where our security lies, that is where our protection lies.
Unhappiness is the weapon satan is using to detach us from Jesus.
This brings us to the title of today’s message: CHEER UP AND CHOOSE JOY.
Tell your neighbour, "Cheer up and choose joy".
Tell your other neighbour, "Cheer up and choose joy".
Let us turn to our Bible to the Book of John 15:11.
This is our Lord Jesus Christ speaking to His disciples.
"I have told you this so that my joy may be in you and that your joy may be complete.“
For our joy to be complete, it must be God’s joy.
Joy is something only believers have.
The world may have happiness they find in their environment.
Just like those two young ladies.
They were happy for a moment and back to sadness.
Joyful for a moment - back to depression.
That is the world.
If your happiness is created by the flesh, it will be interrupted by the flesh.
If you say, "Let me create happiness for myself, I will do this.
Let me drink alcohol“ – the effects of alcohol will soon wear off. Back again.
You say to yourself, "Let me read this book, this novel, this fantasy“.
You get lost in another world, forgetting about your troubles.
The book will soon end.
You watch a film, a soap opera. You watch and you are happy at that moment.
The film will come to an end – back to reality.
Happiness you create for yourself can’t last; it cannot stand the test of time.
Joy is something only believers have because joy is a fruit of faith.
Let’s turn to another scripture.
Philippians 4:4: "Rejoice in the Lord always. I will say it again: Rejoice!“
Does it say there that you should rejoice sometimes, at your convenient time,
when there is money in your pocket, when there is food on the table, when you take a picture?
No, rejoice in the Lord always.
Check yourself.
Whenever our joy seeps out and leaves us barren and empty,
it proves we are out of contact with God, out of fellowship with God.
You begin to see your joy gradually leaving, disappearing, seeping away.
It shows something has happened that has detached you from Jesus – sadness, unhappiness.
This is exactly what satan wants.
Satan’s main aim in tempting people of God is to overthrow their position as children of God,
to cut off their dependence on Him, their duty to Him, their communion with Him.
Satan delights in inflicting pain on people
because he knows that pain may likely separate you from God,
rob you of your joy, rob you of your happiness – that is the devil’s tactic.
Just take time to think about your life.
Any time good news has come, satan will send you some bad news.
Am I talking to someone here? You can check yourself.
Any time there is joy, something wonderful has happened,
satan will quickly send someone to give you some bad news.
He will send you a text message, give you a phone call that will try and scatter your joy.
For many of us, it happened coming to church this morning.
We are on the way to church, happy, joyful, it is going to be a wonderful service.
Suddenly, the phone just rings.
"What happened?"
"Oga, one of your vehicles is spoilt on the road.
The vehicle is a write-off."
You say, "Oh my God! I'm on my way to church.
The vehicle is spoilt. What is going on?
God, do you know I'm coming to worship you?
I'm coming to T.B. Joshua. You go and spoil my vehicle?
Which kind of nonsense is this?"
Many of you will turn back and not even come to church.
Some of you will come to church and as you are sitting down,
you are busy plotting revenge.
The sermon is going on but you are not listening.
You think, "How am I going to pay for this? How am I going to take care of this?
That driver who was in that vehicle - I'm going to deal with him!
Just let the church service come to an end so that I finish it!"
And you are in the church!
Sadness has taken over.
Any time there is happiness, there is joy, there is peace, satan will try and send some bad news.
Just imagine - you heard prophecies here.
Husband and wife looking for a child for so many years - suddenly the pregnancy comes.
There is rejoicing in the home, there is happiness, joy.
Suddenly, a text message comes in from an anonymous person.
"I saw your wife at the club last month with a man.
Are you sure that baby is yours?"
They never sent that text message when your wife was not pregnant.
Why now when there is joy, peace, rejoicing?
Suddenly, someone will try to inflict pain.
Someone will try to bring bad news.
The problem is, so often we make it easy for the devil – we take what we hear without questioning.
You take that text message and say, "Yes, this my wife; she has committed adultery.
She is this" - you don't even examine to know whether it is true.
You just believe.
Many divine marriages have been scattered because of sadness.
Many divine appointments - you are on your way to an appointment
that is going to change your life, rewrite your history.
Satan knows. He will send you bad news.
He will send you bad information to try and discourage you, to try and dishearten you.
And many of us give up at the peak of breakthrough.
Tell your neighbour, "Cheer up and choose joy".
I want to try and practically demonstrate to you the dangers of sadness.
Can I have one volunteer?
Ok, thank you, sir.
Sir, I'm very sorry. You are Mr Sadness.
Yes, I am.
Now, to behave like Mr Sadness, you need to...
I think he is getting it. A little bit more sad, sir.
Thank you. Let's clap for Mr Sadness.
Just for a moment.
Mr Sadness, can you just quickly help me to go to the back.
There is an item there that you are going to make use of for this demonstration.
I just need a couple of chairs and table.
Thank you very much.
I just want to try and practicalise this so that people can understand the danger of sadness.
We don’t know – when we are allowing sadness into our heart, we are allowing destruction.
This is my house. Just for this example.
When I say my house, I mean my heart.
Tell your neighbour, "Your heart".
Remember, the real part about you is your heart.
Take care of your heart. This is the most important part of us, our heart.
God never promised that situations would not come. Where did you read it in the Bible?
This doctrine of no suffering, no health challenges, no hardship, is not in line with the Bible.
It is not scriptural.
Where did you read that as a Christian, you can’t face challenges,
you can’t face difficulty, you can’t have bad news?
No! They come but we overcome.
Who told you that you would not have trouble? That is not scriptural.
Here I am. I am busy, sitting in my house.
Having a great day - there is joy, peace and happiness.
Suddenly, the phone rings.
There are some bad news.
"Dad, you have got to come quickly. Mum is so sick!“
"What? I just left her now. She was fine. What happened?“
"She is really really sick. Please make sure you come as soon as possible.“
Someone you left just yesterday, gone on a business trip and then they say that someone is sick.
Someone is crying; your heart is troubled.
At that moment, Mr Sadness comes in.
Come.
Look. I just had some bad news.
[Knocking.]
What does sadness do? It knocks at the door of your heart.
The question is: Will you open?
[Knocking.]
It knocks on the door. What will you do?
Will you let him in?
Now, in this example, I'm troubled, worried and Mr Sadness knocks.
"Oh, Mr Sadness, come in. Have a seat. Make yourself at home.“
Look. Mr Sadness did not come alone. He brought some items.
He brought some luggage.
So far as you make 'Mr Sadness' feel welcome, he will begin to relax in your heart.
He will begin to be relaxed and feel as if it is his own home.
As he does that, the items in his suitcase, he will begin to bring them out.
Alright. Just bring out some of these items, Mr Sadness.
Alright.
The SCOAN Sunday Service
Look. There are some more items there.
I want you to take a lesson from this.
The moment you allow sadness into your heart, he will begin the work of destruction.
Let me also be clear with you.
When sadness checks in, joy checks out.
The two cannot be in the same house. They are opposite.
There I am busy worrying about my wife that is sick; I'm troubled.
And before you know it, sadness starts dropping in some soap of strife,
toothpaste of past pain, shampoo of shame.
I’m not thinking about this, I’m busy worrying about my problem and Mr Sadness has started to infiltrate.
He started to deposit his evil companions.
And I don’t even know; I’m busy being sad, worrying, depressed.
Before you know it, shame, malice, greed, bitterness, cruelty
because you allowed sadness into your heart.
The SCOAN Sunday Service
Now, this is the painful part.
Most of us Christians come to our senses eventually.
Perhaps you are there and you suddenly remember a message from Prophet T.B. Joshua
talking about the need for you not to focus on your situation but to focus on Jesus.
Suddenly it is as if your eyes open – you look and say, "What is this guy doing here?
Who let you into this house? Get out! Go!"
The SCOAN Sunday Service
Now Mr Sadness has left but he has dropped his toothpaste.
Do you know what happens?
The next day, maybe it is time for you to brush your teeth.
You had a long day; you start brushing your teeth.
"Oh my God, I’m using the toothpaste of past pain!“
Sadness is gone but you are still using his products.
There is the journal of jealousy, the deodorant of discord – you are busy using it.
You don't know that you use something that contaminates your spirit.
The SCOAN Sunday Service
Let me take a bit of water to flush it down.
Bitterness – I have taken the water of bitterness!
Because I have kicked sadness out but he has left his products.
At this point, sadness has been in your heart and he has rigged his destruction, caused this mess.
You now need to start cleaning up, "Jesus, have mercy on me“.
You start repairing what has been damaged, "All of this trouble; no, it is not part of me!"
"Jealousy, I’m a child of God. What has jealousy got to do with me?“
"What is this discord? It has nothing to do with me!"
You throw everything away and start afresh.
"This bag is no longer part of me!“ Throw it away.
Your house is clean. Your heart is clean and free again.
Do you know what happens next?
"Brother, this thing is serious. The company has gone bankrupt. Your shares have all been lost.“
"Eh!"
"Not again! God, why?"
Do you know what happens at that moment?
There is a visitor that will approach.
A visitor will come who wants to start knocking once again.
"Oh God! I have invested so much in that company. What is going on?“
[Knocking.]
"Who is that?"
"Sadness."
"Wait a minute! Isn’t this the guy I just kicked out?
Isn’t this the guy that polluted my house and caused such a mess, chaos and destruction?
Isn't this the same guy?"
But do you know what many of us do?
"Oh, come on in, sir. Have a seat. Come on in, sadness.“
And now, he has brought another bag.
Let us put our hands together for Mr Sadness.
The SCOAN Sunday Service
Mr Sadness, please come with me. I think we need to make you happy.
I think it is time to give you a new name; let's replace sadness with joy.
Come and take one of the altar fruits.
Yes, the sadness has gone now.
The SCOAN Sunday Service
Thank you very much, my brother. You may have your seat.
Let us put our hands together for Jesus.
I want you to reflect on this example.
The cycle of life seems to go on because any time trouble comes, sadness comes back in.
He starts doing his damage, causing his destruction, wreaking his havoc.
When we allow him straight back in, anything we have done to repair the damage,
we ask Jesus, "Come and remove this", we have repaired, removed all of this bitterness,
removed the strife and past pain and then you invite him back in.
Does it not call for concern that we are so welcoming of something so destructive?
You know the damage that has been done; yet, you allow him straight back in.
Those items 'Mr Sadness‘ brought, I’m not referring to physical items
I’m referring to thoughts, suggestions.
By the time sadness is in your heart, you will see it will come with bitterness.
Sadness is in your heart – anger.
Sadness is in your heart – suggestion of pride.
Sadness is in your heart – suggestion of envy, malice, jealousy, things that are contrary to Jesus.
I want to give you a secret today – any time satan wants you to cry, begin to laugh.
This is the greatest embarrassment you can give to satan – to ignore his existence.
He comes with his bad news. You don’t even pay attention.
Nothing interrupts your joy; nothing disturbs your peace
because you know that when satan comes with bad news,
he is simply informing you of the promotion that is coming.
In the face of promotion, why is there need for sadness?
Where is sadness in overcoming and triumph?
When you know that what you are passing through will lead to your promotion, why are you sad?
Tell your neighbour, "Cheer up and choose joy".
There is a story in the Bible we know so well. I want to remind you of it.
The story of Paul and Silas.
Acts 16:25. They were beaten and imprisoned unjustly for the cause of Christ.
There they were in their prison cell at midnight
and the Bible says they began to sing hymns and pray to God and the other prisoners were listening.
Just consider the circumstances under which Paul and Silas began to sing and praise God.
They had been beaten unjustly.
They were doing the work of God.
Paul had just delivered that slave girl from the spirit disturbing her.
They had committed no crime and yet they found themselves in prison.
In the deepest, darkest, deadliest of dungeons.
If it was me or you, we would begin to remind God of how long we have been a Christian.
"God, I have been a member of this church for ten years!
Do you know how much tithe I have given?
Do you know how much offering I have given?
Do you know how many times I have fasted and prayed? Is this how you repay me?"
Sadness.
Paul and Silas were in prison physically but their hearts were free.
They praised God.
Satan may succeed in inflicting you with pain but don’t let him pain your heart.
He may succeed in tampering with your business, causing some financial challenges.
Don’t let him tamper with your heart.
Satan may succeed in imprisoning you; you may end up in prison for what you know nothing about.
Don’t let him imprison your spirit, your heart.
Take a leaf from Paul and Silas and in the face of life’s challenges,
life's bad news, life’s ups and downs, begin to sing and praise God.
Choose the bright colours of praise
rather than the dark colours of doubt, discouragement and depression.
I'm going to round up but I want to share with you a very personal expereince
that solidified and strengthened my faith to give such a message.
It was over 10 years ago.
This is an incidence that many of us that are new to Emmanuel TV might not be familiar with.
But if you have been in this church for many years, you will be aware of what happened.
Many years, over 10 years ago, Emmanuel TV was new, fresh, changing lives, nations and the world.
One day after the service on Sunday, it was in the early hours of Monday morning.
Around 2 to 3 am, we were all here in the church.
Suddenly came the alarm. I remember it very vividly.
Someone came to my bed and hit me and said, "There is fire!“
Everyone was scattered; there was pandemonium, worry, panic.
We rushed down.
The church console, the control room, the heart of Emmanuel TV was in flames.
Everyone started running up and down, getting water, trying to reduce the flames.
I was worried. At that moment, sadness had entered my heart.
I was distressed.
"God, this is equipment worth millions. What is going on? How could this happen?“
As everyone was busy, rushing to do this or that, I remember this so well –
I heard someone laughing and I was provoked.
"How can you laugh! This situation does not call for laughter, joy! This is a serious situation!“
The same person I heard laughing was asking people, „How are you?“, smiling and greeting people.
I looked round and I saw Prophet T.B. Joshua.
He came to me, gave me a big smile and said, „How are you?“
I didn’t say anything.
I was shocked.
The situation on the ground did not call for that.
He was so relaxed, so joyful.
He was even calling people, "Make sure you bring a camera to camera it“.
"What? You have just lost equipment worth millions! Oh my God!
There was joy.
By the grace of God, everything was resolved; the fire didn’t spread anywhere else.
Afterwards, that morning, Prophet T.B. Joshua gathered all the evangelists and workers that were there
and said, "God allowed this and I knew it would happen“.
He said, "Out of these ashes will shine forth beauty“.
Today, our control room is ten times better than the one that was lost.
Why am I saying this, brethren?
This personal experience, example in the life of Prophet T.B. Joshua?
I do not know what you are passing through right now.
Viewers, I don’t know what situation you are in.
Perhaps your marriage is on fire.
Perhaps your business is on fire.
Perhaps your finances are on fire.
One thing I do know, as a Christian, out of those ashes, beauty will come.
If you can just glimpse the bigger picture.
Beyond that trial, there is triumph.
Beyond that scar, there is a star.
Beyond that mess is a message.
If we could just catch the bigger picture.
Beyond that painful story is beautiful glory.
As a child of God, where then is sadness?
Why do we so easily give our hearts to sadness, depression, unhappiness as Christians?
In John 16:33 Jesus said, "In this world, you will have trouble but cheer up; take heart.
Choose joy because you will overcome“.
Brethren, let me not deceive you.
Trouble will come but you will overcome.
Sickness will come but you will overcome.
Hardship will come but you will overcome.
Stop trading your joy for your situation.
Don’t let anything rob you of joy – joy is our conquering power.
The joy of the Lord is our strength (Nehemiah 8:10).
Affliction may test me as a man of faith but it cannot rob me of my joy.
Trouble may test me as a man of faith but it cannot rob me of my joy
and when I cheer up and choose joy, my test will turn into a testimony.
I don’t know what tomorrow holds but I know who holds tomorrow.
Rejoice because the higher Hand that is leading you, is leading you to something higher.
May God bless His Word in the midst of our hearts, in Jesus‘ name.
TT: Mel Flowers 14/12/2018
rv robert begier 29/03/2019